#### **INSTRUMENTATION ENGINEER**



#### **PRAVEEN**

Email: <u>praveeneie42@gmail.com</u>

Mob: +91 8072360822

### Objective:

As an instrumentation engineer with more than 6 years of experience in Industrial Automation and Control systems, maintenance of manufacturing machines, calibration, project management and technical support, automation software design and development. Established proficiency in implementing creative solutions and architecture, problem resolution and management for new and existing systems for various industries like: Food & Beverage, Automotive, Metals, Material handling, Footwear, RO treatment & Fertilizers.

# **Professional Experience: 6+ Years**

**Company: 1 : VOLGA Tech,**(December 2016-present)

**Designation**: Maintenance Engineer (E&M)

### **Roles and Responsibilities:**

- Coordinating with the maintenance team to ensure no unscheduled breakdowns through condition monitoring, of the machines and performance.
- Conduct troubleshooting in cases of process related problem/process disturbances and necessary action whenever required.
- Responsible for timely completion of the agreed project within the planned cost and coordinating with the vendors & assist in planning of new equipment installs.
- Maintain plant log & Maintenance Technician's work list and assure it is completed in a safe and timely manner.
- Oversee and schedule maintenance on all plant processing equipment including routine and preventative maintenance Schedule.
- Make sure all exterior and interior repairs are scheduled or completed as needed
- Ensure all plant processes are operating mechanically &electrically to plant standards and expectations
- Conduct bi-weekly safety meetings with maintenance personnel on various topics and document meeting with signatures from all attendees

Company: 2 : RNZ INTERNATIONAL FZE, Dubai.(December 2014-October 2016)

**Designation**: **Instrumentation Engineer (Maintenance)** 

# Roles and Responsibilities:

> To carry out planned preventive maintenance and breakdown repair on all high volume manufacturing machinery on site.

- > Electrical fault finding and maintenance, preventative maintenance and breakdown repair. Optimization of the Maintenance Organization structure
- Analysis of repetitive equipment failures
- Estimation of maintenance costs and evaluation of alternatives
- Forecasting of spare parts, assessing the needs for equipment replacements and establish replacement programs when due
- Application of scheduling and project management principles to replacement programs
- Assessing required maintenance tools and skills required for efficient maintenance of equipment
- Assessing required skills required for maintenance personnel
- Reviewing personnel transfers to and from maintenance organizations
- Assessing and reporting safety hazards associated with maintenance of equipment

**Company: 3**: Maxine Automation (November 2012-October 2014)

**Designation**: Application Engineer (Industrial Automation)

Products: PLC-(Siemens, Delta, Mitsubishi, Omron) HMI-(Siemens, Delta, Omron)

VFD(Danfoss, Siemens, Omron, Yaskawa, ABB, AB, Delta, Schneider Electric, Vacon, Toshiba, Mitsubishi) HMI's, AC Servo Drives, Switch Gears,

Sensors, Temperature controllers, Field instruments.

# Roles and Responsibilities:

- ✓ Programming of PLC ,HMI,VFD through the respective software & communicating with third party devices.
- ✓ Installation, commissioning and erection of Automation products as well as their supporting tool and services.
- ✓ Assisting customer to understand all products and perform demo for field applications.
- ✓ Install and configure PLC system and perform troubleshoot on process and resolve issues.
- ✓ Provide Technical support to customer and configure on Automation products.

- ✓ Analyze customer requirement and ensure product meet customer requirements appropriately.
- ✓ Administer various field applications for customers and provide support to software.
- ✓ Perform troubleshoot on controller issues and perform tests on bugs.
- ✓ Develop and determine various product features, perform tests for same.

#### **PROJECTS REFERENCES**

- ✓ PEPSICO Holdings India(PET bottle filler Automation for conveyors)
- √ VKC (PLC based Automation for Footwear machine)
- ✓ Savio (Pneumatic based automation and VFD for testing machine)
- ✓ Installation, commissioning and erection of VFD upto 100KW.
- ✓ SPM(Various SPM based on PLC automation in Hydraulic &Pneumatic Machine)
- ✓ Automatic PLC Control for RO Waste water Treatment for Pumps and Control Valves.

Company: 4 LAKSHMI AUTOMATION (June 2011-July 2012)

(Authorized DELTA Dealer)

**Designation:** Application Engineer (Industrial Automation)

Products: PLC-DELTA, VFD-DELTA, HMI-DELTA, AC Servo - DELTA

# **ROLES & RESPONSIBILITIES**

- ✓ Programming, Installation, commissioning and erection of DELTA Automation products as well As their supporting tool and services
- ✓ Making of Proposals, Estimation, And Project Costing.
- ✓ Technical compliance to the contractors and clients.
- ✓ System Integration, Software Configuration, Customizing and Designing.
- ✓ Provide Technical support to customer and configure services on Automation products
- ✓ Installation, commissioning and erection of Automation products.

### **PROJECTS REFERENCES**

- ✓ Roots Cast India (Automation for ROBO ARM for Dye Molding Machine and various Hydraulic Press)
- ✓ PEPSICO Holdings India(Chiller Plant Automation for compressor)
- ✓ SPM(Various SPM based on PLC automation in Hydraulic &Pneumatic Machine)
- ✓ ELGI Equipment's(RETROFIT of Honning Machine)

**Company: 5 AB AUTOMATION** (September 2010-May 2011)

(Panel builder)

**Designation:** Instrumentation Engineer (Industrial Automation)

Products: Automation Panels, HT,LT,ELV Panels, Sensors, RTD,

Thermocouple, PLC-DELTA, VFD-DELTA, HMI-DELTA, AC Servo

### **ROLES & RESPONSIBILITIES**

- Programming, Installation, commissioning and erection of Automation products as well
   As their supporting tool and services
- ✓ Provide Technical support to customer and configure services on Automation products
- ✓ Installation, commissioning and erection of Automation products.

### **EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATIONS**

✓ Bachelor of Engineer – Electronics & Instrumentation Engineering, Anna University, India (2010)

#### TRAININGS ATTENDED

✓ Participated in Autonomous Robotics Workshop Conducted by TRI solutions SINE, IIT, Mumbai.

#### **CERTIFICATION COURSES**

✓ Automation Course (PLC, SCADA and DCS) Certified from HONEYWELL AUTOMATION INDIA Ltd., PUNE.

#### **COMPUTER KNOWLEDGE**

- ✓ Operating System Windows 98/XP ,Windows 7,Window 8
- ✓ MS Office.
- ✓ C,C++

### **PERSONAL DETAILS**

Name Praveen
Date of Birth 15-12-1987

Sex Male
Nationality Indian
Marital Status Unmarried

Languages Known English, Malayalam, Tamil, Hindi

Permanent Address Mathilakam, Sasthankarai, Colachel (p.o) 629251

Kanya kumari District, Tamil Nadu, India

Passport Number: J 3346367

### **DECLARATION**

I hereby declare that the above information and facts are true to the best of my knowledge and belief.

Date: Yours Faithfully Place: (PRAVEEN)